Pesach פסח, Pesach, good Chodesh חודש, Chodesh, fifty days of the Omer
עומר, Omer, and our daf דף Daf is Tes Amud Beis ט
עמוד ב Tes Amud Beis we will start with, or had it
yesterday, we'll probably do Tes Amud Beis ט עמוד ב Tes Amud
Beis and Yud י Yud today. And we pick from the top
of the Amud Beis עמוד ב, Amud Beis, and we have a
basic machlokes מחלוקת Machlokes here between Rav רב Rav and, who's it
between? Between Rav רב Rav and Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
about whether there is me'ilah מעילה Me'ilah on the ashes before they
are taken out to the beis hadeshen בית הדשן Beis Hadeshen after
terumas hadeshen תרומת הדשן Terumas Hadeshen is done. Simple sense of the
Mishnah משנה Mishnah is that there is me'ilah מעילה Me'ilah on til
for things that are burnt on the mizbeiach מזבח Mizbeiach until it's
all taken out, until it's taken out to the beis hadeshen בית
הדשן. Beis Hadeshen. That's considered that the mitzvah מצווה Mitzvah still remains
to be done. But Rav רב Rav says no, that once you
have terumas hadeshen תרומת הדשן, Terumas Hadeshen, it is no longer, there
is no longer me'ilah מעילה. Me'ilah. Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
emphasizes since the, not the original terumas hadeshen תרומת הדשן Terumas Hadeshen
of the morning, but since the cleaning out of the ashes to
the outside of the environment of the mikdash מקדש, Mikdash, bigdei kehunah
בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehunah, it's also an avodah עבודה Avodah and therefore
it's not considered that the mitzvos מצוות Mitzvos are not yet done
with the things that are burnt. So let's take a look. Tes
Amud Beis ט עמוד ב Tes Amud Beis to try to see
it one way or the other. Meiseiv מיתיבי, Meiseiv, very top of
Tes Amud Beis ט עמוד ב. Tes Amud Beis. Vechulan shepaku mei'agabi
hamizbeiach lo yachazir וכולן שפקעו מעל גבי המזבח לא יחזיר. Vechulan shepaku
mei'agabi hamizbeiach lo yachazir.
So this is a Mishnah משנה Mishnah in Zevachim זבחים Zevachim that
teaches about what types of things you put on the mizbeiach מזבח.
Mizbeiach. So certain things, certain things you don't, like you don't put
the horns on the, horns on the mizbeiach מזבח Mizbeiach or the
hair on the mizbeiach מזבח. Mizbeiach. But it says, but if you
sort of put them on together with the skin, then you do
put them on the mizbeiach מזבח. Mizbeiach. Or if you put them
on, as you know, general rule is even certain things you're not
supposed to put on, once they're there you don't take them off.
So if you put on you don't take it off, but it
says if they actually popped off, paku פקעו, Paku, like popped off,
goes a little bit onomatopoeic.
Anyway, so it says, but if they were put on and then
they fell off, then don't put them back on. Okay fine, that's
not exactly relevant for us. But now the next point is. Vechon
gacheles shepaku mei'agabi hamizbeiach lo yachazir וכן גחלת שפקעו מעל גבי המזבח
לא יחזיר. Vechon gacheles shepaku mei'agabi hamizbeiach lo yachazir. If you have
a coal that obviously of some normal stuff, not necessarily of these
things. Normal coal from, you know, normal coal.
What? Now
wood. Now it's not right. Rashi רש"י Rashi makes the point that
it is, or Pseudo-Rashi פסודו-רש"י, Pseudo-Rashi, whatever, that it is not from
the burnt innards of a korban קרבן, Korban, this is just normal
wood. Okay, so wood that fell off the mizbeiach מזבח, Mizbeiach, don't
put it back on. Okay, because then presumably it's no longer, you
know, it's already turned to charcoal, it's already to some degree it's
like na'aseh mitzvaso נעשה מצוותו, Na'aseh mitzvaso, but we're not going to
get into the na'aseh mitzvaso נעשה מצוותו Na'aseh mitzvaso question about the
normal wood. Okay, we're going to start focusing on, let's read the
next line. Okay,
ha'agabi mizbeiach yachazir הא גבי מזבח יחזיר. Ha'agabi mizbeiach yachazir. If it
was all on the mizbeiach מזבח Mizbeiach you do put it back.
Now, I'm sorry, what did I mean?
I meant that you would basically have, you know, you'd have a
big pile of ashes in the middle, then you'd have like the
little fires, the stuff that was actively burning on the sides. Okay,
and let me just re-check Rashi רש"י Rashi again just for a
second before I say this. Okay, so Rashi רש"י,
Rashi,
yeah no, the problem is that Rashi רש"י Rashi is saying that
we are talking
about the... okay, anyway. Rashi רש"י Rashi made,
Rashi's רש"י Rashi a little bit concerned because I'm going to bracket
that for now if you want to go back to that point,
that's very annoying. But the question here is do you remember that
both Rav רב Rav and Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan agree
that before terumas hadeshen תרומת הדשן Terumas Hadeshen there is me'ilah מעילה.
Me'ilah. So the question is here how do we know whether we're
talking about before or after terumas hadeshen תרומת הדשן? Terumas Hadeshen? So
I'm going to bracket that question for now, that's a point that
Rashi רש"י Rashi addresses and says we're taking it for granted we're
talking after terumas hadeshen תרומת הדשן. Terumas Hadeshen. Let's bracket that right
now. And then the point is, and how does Rashi רש"י Rashi
say we're taking that for granted? He says because we're assuming that
we're dealing with something that came from the big mound of ashes
in the middle. Okay, you put stuff on the fire, it, you
know, it turns into charcoal or whatever, and as that fell off,
that's before terumas hadeshen תרומת הדשן, Terumas Hadeshen, that's when the thing
is still first turning into ashes. And then Rashi רש"י Rashi says
that would be obvious you put that back, there's still me'ilah מעילה
Me'ilah and so on. It fell off from straight on the fire.
So Rashi רש"י Rashi therefore emphasizes, again, it's not explicit in the
Mishnah משנה Mishnah until Tosafos תוספות Tosafos or another way of dealing
with it, we're not talking about the new meat that was put
on directly on the fire, that would not be na'aseh mitzvaso נעשה
מצוותו Na'aseh mitzvaso until terumas hadeshen תרומת הדשן. Terumas Hadeshen. We're either
talking about firewood, or we're talking about stuff that after the terumas
hadeshen תרומת הדשן Terumas Hadeshen was done, you would scoop all the
ashes, you know, from the fires into the main central ashes place.
So when something is coming from the main central ashes place, that's
stuff that already terumas hadeshen תרומת הדשן Terumas Hadeshen was come from.
And now we're talking about that. If it fell off, you know,
no one minute. That's why you know that terumas hadeshen תרומת הדשן
Terumas Hadeshen was done. Now, it says if it fell off. off
the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, you don't put it back. Okay. That you would
say maybe is evidence in itself, but apparently there's an assumption here
that when stuff falls off the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, that maybe it changes
its status and makes it means that you're done with it. So
that's not so much the point. The point is that if it
moves from the ashes pile to a different place on the מזבח,
Mizbe'ach, and that's what it means פקע paka here, that then even
there, in that case, you would put it back in the ashes
pile. Let's start again. If it moves from the main ashes pile,
okay,
and it moves from one minute, yeah. So
back to what I was
saying, I'm sorry, if
it moves from the main ashes pile and it goes to one
of the fires, so you had stuff basically, the point is, this
is getting complicated as רש״י Rashi is trying to figure out how
we don't know this yet from תרומת הדשן. Terumat HaDeshen. So let
me simplify it a little bit. Basically, the point is, is you've
got some stuff of some קרבן korban that's been burning. We're going
to assume that there was already תרומת הדשן. Terumat HaDeshen. We're going
to assume that it already turned into a coal, okay? It is
ashes, it is a coal in תרומת הדשן, Terumat HaDeshen, and what
does it say happens? It says that it falls off, then you
then you don't put it back on the main fire, any fire,
you leave it off the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. But the תוספתא Tosefta itself,
if it fell off the fire, if it came off the fire
and it fell to a place on the מזבח Mizbe'ach that there
is no fire, there wasn't one big fire, there were little fires,
there was a big ashes place, if it fell to a place
that there was no fire, then you put it back on fire.
Okay? And that's the question: why? Why do you put it back
on the fire? It had become ashes, there was already תרומת הדשן,
Terumat HaDeshen, why would you bother putting it back on the fire?
Why wouldn't you just, you know, now of course you could say,
well, it's easier to put it back on the fire than to
be what, but who knows? Okay, why would you do that? That
indicates somehow that you haven't yet finished, it's not yet the מצוה.
mitzvah.
So let me understand the sequence. I don't understand the like the
sequence of תרומת הדשן, Terumat HaDeshen, because you had these little fires
on the side, a big one in the middle, right?
Well, in the middle you have the ashes, not a fire.
Well, you have the מערכה גדולה. Ma'aracha Gedola.
Oh, yeah, that's okay, yeah.
So you have the מערכה גדולה Ma'aracha Gedola and then מערכה שניה
Ma'aracha Sheniya of קטורת Ketoret or whatever, right, you know.
So from the big one, you would put some you know you
take from the big one in the top and you put it
on like the side of the מזבח Mizbe'ach where the אימורים imurim
are, you know, like let's say where they throw the חטאת העוף,
chatat ha'of, that same place? Like the...
what I don't know what are you asking? After it burns on
the fire, you move it to the ash pile. Can we not
worry about that right now because we're going to have all that
in the המשך? hemshech? Okay, okay. Anyway, let's pick up let's keep
on going. So it says like this. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: הא גבי מזבח. ha gabei Mizbe'ach. Okay, so it
says that's what it read, דקתני הכא שפקע מעל גבי מזבח. dekateni
hacha shepaka me'al gabei Mizbe'ach. You have something that is a coal
that fell off the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, לא יחזיר, lo yachazir, don't put
it back. And somehow that's not seen in itself as indicative that
the מצוה mitzvah is done, because maybe it's assumed that falling off
of the מזבח Mizbe'ach is different. Okay, הא... ha... not exactly clear
to me why, but okay, הא על גבי מזבח יחזיר. ha al
gabei Mizbe'ach yachazir. If it's still on the מזבח Mizbe'ach and it
moved from the fire to another place in the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, you
put it back, even though it was already turned into coal and
even though presumably תרומת הדשן Terumat HaDeshen already took place. How do
we know תרומת הדשן Terumat HaDeshen took place is not so clear,
that's where I started it started getting complicated, I could go back
to that, but let's just work with that for now. So you
see בשלמא לרבי יוחנן ניחא. bishlama le-Rabbi Yochanan nicha. According to רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that says that there still is מעילה me'ilah until
you take the stuff out to the ashes pile, then it's good,
meaning the simple way of saying this is, look, according to רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, there are very specific things you do with them
even after תרומת הדשן, Terumat HaDeshen, which is what you have to
do מצוה mitzvah of taking it out to, you know, to take
it out and you do have to do הוצאת הדשן. Hotza'at HaDeshen.
So according to him, there's still מצוות mitzvot to be done, we
understand why you're moving things back into the right place and so
on, there's still particular things to be done with it. But according
to
רב Rav though, אלא לרב קשיא. ela le-Rav kashya. According to רב,
Rav, what
who cares what you do with it? יחזיר, yachazir, לא יחזיר, lo
yachazir, who cares? You've already done תרומת הדשן, Terumat HaDeshen, it's already
turned into coals, so you're done. So you want to be מחזיר,
machazir, fine, you don't want to be מחזיר, machazir, fine, who cares?
You're already done. That's the גמרא's Gemara question. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara answers. אמר לך רב, Amar lach Rav, רב Rav
would say here: לא שאני גחלת דאית בה מששא. lo, shani gachelet
d'it bah mashasha. A coal is different, that there is some substance.
It's not just pure ashes. And what here he's basically saying is,
that's interesting because there's a whole discussion of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש
Rabbi Yochanan ve-Resh Lakish in בבא קמא Bava Kamma about a גחלת
gachelet and the and the whatever the if you
if you give a גחלת gachelet to a to a child and
he and he lights a fire. אית בה מששא, אית בה מששא.
it bah mashasha, it bah mashasha. Anyway, similar language. Anyway, what he's
saying is a גחלת, gachelet, there still is burning left to be
done. Meaning when when I say that the מצוה mitzvah is done,
even before you take it outside the מחנה, machaneh,
that's ashes. It's not a coal. A coal still has to turn
into ashes, so there there is still left to be done with
the מצוה. mitzvah. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, others say: ולהך גיסא, u-le-hach
gisa, that the
evidence was brought initially the other way. טעמא משום גחלת דאית בה
מששא, Ta'ama mishum gachelet d'it bah mashasha, the only reason that you
move it back and would care about it is because it's a
coal and there still is some substance and it could still be
turned into ashes. הא אפר דלית בה מששא, Ha efer d'leit bah
mashasha, but pure ashes and you didn't have
that, אפילו גבי מזבח אין מחזירין afillu gabei Mizbe'ach ein machazirin though.
Now again, this משנה mishnah never... And that should be an evidence
to רב. Rav. בשלמא לרב ניחא, bishlama leRav nicha, for רב Rav
it's
good, the only reason you care is that it's still a
coal. אלא לרב יוחנן קשיא, ela leRav Yochanan kashya, according to רב
יוחנן Rav Yochanan it's difficult
because even after it's ashes we care what gets done with it,
so why should it sound like we don't care?
אמר לך רב יוחנן, amar lach Rav Yochanan, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
would say back to you, הוא הדין דאפילו אפר, hu hadin d'afilu
efer, it would be too even ashes, והאי דתני גחלת, vehai detani
gachelet, so why did we say a coal? קא
משמע לן דאפילו גחלת דאית בה מששא ka mashma lan d'afilu gachelet
de'it bah mashasha
to tell you even something that still has some substance and still
could be burned and turned into ashes, כי פקע מעל גבי מזבח
לא יחזיר, ki paka me'al gabbei mizbeach lo yachzir, that
you don't care about it when it falls off the מזבח. mizbeach.
Now that's really what's not clear. The גמרא Gemara doesn't even bother
itself when it falls off the מזבח, mizbeach, that normally when things
fall off the מזבח mizbeach you would say if it's פסול pasul
and only got there because it doesn't belong to be there and
we're leaving it there when it falls off, we're not going to
put it back. But it's actually not so clear why something that
was כשר, kasher, that wasn't a hundred percent done, why not put
it back? But anyway that seems, that's not our issue and the
גמרא Gemara isn't addressing that right now and it says fine, the
reason we said that is to tell you even that which still
had burning left, once it fell off, we don't worry about it.
Okay, this anyway is the debate and here we get a little
insight into רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan though or into רב, Rav, that
רב Rav says when I say it's done before you take it
out, that's only when it turns to ashes. When it's still a
coal, it's not yet done and therefore you would move it back
to the right place. So if it fell off the fire, you'd
move it back onto the fire in order that it could turn
into ashes. So I realize I was being a little
overly complicated before, but I was trying to introduce רב Rav which
I shouldn't have, because there is a question here which is, how
do we know this happened before the תרומת הדשן? Trumas Hadeshen? I
mean, after the תרומת הדשן? Trumas Hadeshen? Maybe it happened before the
תרומת הדשן? Trumas Hadeshen? And I will just give you, רש"י Rashi
has this complicated scenario which I'm not going to bother with because
anyway it's complicated and... No. That's
not a good word. I will tell you though תוספות's Tosafot point
because it's important about this question about the significance of תרומת הדשן
Trumas Hadeshen and this is I think an issue that Michael asked
yesterday. So let me just let me just double check תוספות Tosafot
before I say it, one minute. Okay
so
what תוספות Tosafot says is like this: why did we say that
everybody agrees there is מעילה me'ilah before תרומת הדשן? Trumas Hadeshen? That
everybody agrees that before תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen there's still a מצוה
mitzvah to be done with this. What's the מצוה mitzvah to be
done? The מצוה mitzvah of תרומת הדשן. Trumas Hadeshen. The problem is,
or not the problem, the question is what do you mean there's
a מצוה mitzvah to do תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen with this? You
have to do it with these ashes? You can do תרומת הדשן
Trumas Hadeshen with any of these ashes. So the way I explained
it yesterday was, okay, it doesn't necessarily mean you have to take
these ashes out for תרומת הדשן, Trumas Hadeshen, but to some degree
they have to be part of the ashes to which תרומת הדשן
Trumas Hadeshen is being done. Okay, that's how I explained what it
means that there's still a מצוה mitzvah to be done with these
until תרומת הדשן. Trumas Hadeshen.
תוספות Tosafot says he frames it a little bit differently. Now what
he says is, is that when we say there's still a מצוה
mitzvah of תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen to be done to them, it
means that there's still is the potential that they can be used
for תרומת הדשן. Trumas Hadeshen. And therefore they're not yet done. So
he says that's why it doesn't matter in this case if תרומת
הדשן Trumas Hadeshen was done or not. Since it was פקע, paka,
since it moved to a part of the מזבח mizbeach where the
ashes are not normally gathered, whether it was starting from a fire,
starting from the ashes pile, wherever it moved, it moved to some
random place on the מזבח. mizbeach. Off the מזבח? mizbeach? No, no,
no, פקע paka off certainly, but we're talking even on, then it's
not yet it's no longer in the category where מצוה mitzvah תרומת
הדשן Trumas Hadeshen could be done to it. It's no longer part
of the collection of ashes to which I would normally do תרומת
הדשן. Trumas Hadeshen. So therefore he says it's not in a category
of נעשה מצותו, na'aseh mitzvato, because for the time being it's moved
to a place where that מצוה mitzvah is no longer relevant. Okay,
so that's interesting. You could say what do you mean, all the
more so it's not נעשה מצותו, na'aseh mitzvato, it's not in a
place where you can do the מצוה, mitzvah, you have to move
it back. Anyway, that's what תוספות Tosafot says and he's trying to
address that. But this case is, that's an interesting point just because
what does it mean נעשה מצותו na'aseh mitzvato of תרומת הדשן Trumas
Hadeshen if you don't necessarily have to use these ashes? So תוספות
Tosafot says more because you have to have them in the case
where they have the potential of being used. I would have framed
it more as I told you that they're part of the ashes
pile to which the תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen is being done. But
anyway what you have is the following though: you have here according
to according to רב Rav who doesn't need הוצאת הדשן, hotza'at hadeshen,
he still needs it to go from coal to ashes to be
considered נעשה מצותו, na'aseh mitzvato, and you have this interesting debate here
where somehow we have to... where about things moved around, how do
we know we're talking after תרומת הדשן? Trumas Hadeshen? רש"י Rashi makes
it a special case, but תוספות Tosafot actually says that not all
times do we say תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen matters. It only matters
in terms of נעשה מצותו na'aseh mitzvato if it's in a position
where it could be used for תרומה.
Trumas. Now whether the little side fires, if you don't do הוצאת
הדשן Hotza'as Hadeshen for there too, then it shouldn't make a difference
if it's on the side.
Yeah, I don't know, I haven't thought that through.
Okay fine,
I haven't thought that through.
Yes. But what exactly is תרומת הדשן? Terumas Hadeshen?
Every morning, actually after midnight, doesn't even have to be after daybreak,
you take a, it's a symbolic removal of a, of a like
a scoop of ash that you take from the ashes, from the
inner part of all the stuff that's been burnt, the inner part
of the ash pile and you put it at the side of
the altar, set it right next to the ramp. So that is
different than הוצאת הדשן, Hotza'as Hadeshen, right? We mentioned this yesterday, which
is the cleaning off of it, which is done every few days
when it gets too much and you take all the ashes outside
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so everybody agrees that before the
תרומת הדשן Terumas Hadeshen there still is מעילה Me'ilah by the ashes.
Okay, and the question is why? You don't necessarily use these particular
ashes in תרומת הדשן. Terumas Hadeshen. So רש"י Rashi is afraid you
get because it has to be part of the ashes from which
תרומת הדשן Terumas Hadeshen is taken and therefore it's not yet, they're
not yet done because they have to be still at least part
of the pile from which it's taken.
And what happens to that little pile of תרומת הדשן?
Terumas Hadeshen? Well, according to the מדרש Midrash it gets, according to
the גמרא Gemara it gets absorbed into the ground. Okay, so, but
whatever gets done with it, it's done. It's no longer...
One other quick question about the word. I always thought the word
was ממש. Mamash. Why משש? Mashash?
Oh, I think that they're interchangeable but that's a good point. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. איתמר. Itmar. הנהנה מבשר קדשי
קדשים לפני זריקת דמים. Haneheneh mibesar kodshei kodashim lifnei zerikas damim. ואימורי
קדשים קלים לאחר זריקת דמים. Ve'imurei kodashim kalim le'achar zerikas damim. Okay,
so now
we are going to get into a very different conversation, although at
the end we will circle back to רב Rav and רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. So now we have that one question: When do you
say נעשה מצותו Na'aseh mitzvato by normal things that are burnt? After
תרומת הדשן Terumas Hadeshen or after it's actually taken out? Now we
get to this question of,
what do you do, which is really completely irrelevant to our discussion,
but nevertheless, what do when you have to give money back for
מעילה, Me'ilah, where does that money go? Good question. If you stole
from the Temple treasury, the money you give back plus the fifth
goes back to the Temple treasury. Let's say you did מעילה Me'ilah
from a קרבן. Korban. Where does the money go? Now if I
haven't bought the קרבן Korban yet, if it's from קרבן Korban money,
then easy, I increase, give it back and I now buy the
קרבן Korban or give or bring more קרבן Korban money. But let's
say I actually got הנאה Hana'ah from this animal. Okay, the animal
was brought, the קרבן Korban was an animal. I rode on it
or whatever, I didn't steal it, even though I did steal, it
doesn't really matter, I'm חייב מעילה chayav Me'ilah plus a fifth. What
do I do? I now give it back to the קרבן, Korban,
but this is the קרבן. Korban. And let's say the קרבן Korban
was already brought. Let's say it was a חטאת. Chatas. I give
another חטאת? Chatas? I'm חייב חטאת. chayav Chatas. What do you do
with that money? How do you give it back to the, you
know, in a sense, how do you replace what was, where the
benefit came from?
Meaning what? Like if I was נהנה neheneh in the כהן's Kohen's
portion, I'd think I'd have to pay the כהן Kohen part. If
I was נהנה neheneh in, let's say, the שלמים Shelamim and...
Maybe, but let's say you were נהנה neheneh while it was alive.
Let's say you were נהנה neheneh from the part that goes on
the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
איתמר. Itmar. הנהנה מבשר קדשי קדשים לפני זריקת דמים. Haneheneh mibesar kodshei
kodashim lifnei zerikas damim. Let's say you got הנאה Hana'ah from the
meat of קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim before זריקת דם. zerikas dam.
After it's dead.
Now even, by the
way, even, even after זריקת דמים zerikas damim I should mention, you
might go it's not so obvious you give it to
the כהנים Kohanim because you didn't steal from the כהנים, Kohanim, you
stole
from הקדש Hekdesh and you have to give it back to הקדש.
Hekdesh. You're not just paying them for a steak dinner. So anyway,
let's see what it says. ואימורי קדשים קלים לאחר זריקת דמים. Ve'imurei
kodashim kalim le'achar zerikas damim. Or the אימורין imurin of קדשים קלים
kodashim kalim after זריקת דמים. zerikas damim. So both of these cases,
you got benefit from something that nobody yet could, that was only
for the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Right? What are you going to do with
it? So רב אמר מה שנהנה יפלו לנדבה. Rav amar mah she'neheneh
yipelu lindavah. Take the money, buy an עולה. Olah. A נדבה Nedavah
is an עולת ציבור. Olas tzibbur. Give an עולת ציבור, Olas tzibbur,
at least it gets on the מזבח Mizbe'ach and it's a קרבן,
Korban, so it's roughly the same. ולוי אמר יביא דבר שכולו למזבח.
Veleivi amar yavi davar shekulo lamizbe'ach. You bring something that
goes completely on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. You would think that's the עולה,
Olah, but no, not all the עולה. Olah. You have the עור,
or, the skin and so on. So what's more on the מזבח
Mizbe'ach than the עולה? Olah? So let's take a look. תני כוותיה
דלוי מנחת כהנים. Tani kevasei deLeivi minchas Kohanim. Yeah, and what makes
a מנחת כהנים? minchas Kohanim? תני כוותיה דלוי. Tani kevasei deLeivi. מעילה
זו להיכן הולכת. Me'ilah zu leheichan holeches. Where does this מעילה Me'ilah
go? הלומדים לפני חכמים אומרים. Halomdim lifnei chachamim omrim. Those that would
learn in front of the sages would say, I'll get back to
who that is in a minute, יביא דבר שכולו למזבח. yavi davar
shekulo lamizbe'ach. Bring something that's all for the altar. מאי ניהו? Mai
nihu? What is that? קטורת. Ketores. It's the קטורת. Ketores. קטורת, Ketores,
the incense, if you donate to the incense for the, then all
of that gets completely burnt.
Like the wood would too, right?
Well, possibly, it's interesting, they say probably not because you want something
that is a קרב, karev, it's a קרבן, Korban, not the fuel.
Okay, so you do want to be giving back a קרבן. Korban.
So the idea is is that you stole from a קרבן Korban
that is on the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, you have to give back from
that that goes to the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, and you give whatever is
the closest approximation. Now, are you going to give money for, you
don't actually
bring the קטורת Ketores because the כהנים Kohanim
have to do that, right?
Right, you give it over fully to the ציבור. Tzibbur. Okay, or
there's a question about whether you can be נודב קטורת nodev Ketores
for the מזבח החיצון Mizbe'ach hachitzon or something. But anyway, right. So
yes. So that is the exact question about how you give קטורת.
Ketores. Anyway, but something that would be burnt fully. Now,
now the point I want to say is two things. First of
all... Okay, who are הלימידיי לפני חכמים *halimeday lifnay chachamim*? In the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* it says that that's לוי *Levi*
who would learn before רבי *Rebbe*. Now that would be funny. It
shows us, first of all it says תניא כוותיה דלוי *Tanya kevasay
d'Levi*, there's a ברייתא *Baraita* that לוי *Levi* himself is saying it.
That's not exactly תניא כוותיה *Tanya kevasay*. Number two is לוי *Levi*
is the generation after the תנאים *Tannaim*. He's never quoted in the
משנה mishna *Mishna*, in the ברייתות *Baraitot*. So here it would be
referring to לוי *Levi*, that we never have that before. So תוספות
Tosafos *Tosafot* says it has to be somebody else, he doesn't know
who it is, but in another גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it says at
least this phrase sometimes means לוי *Levi*. Number one. Number two, it
is interesting that although you are נהנה ne'eneh *neheneh* from the בשר
קדשי קדשים basar kadshei kodoshim *basar kodshay kodashim*, at least the אימורי
קדשים קלים kodshim kalim *imuray kodashim kalim* would be burnt on the
מזבח mizbeach. *mizbayach*. בשר basar קדשי קדשים kadshei kodoshim *Basar kodshay kodashim*
would go
to the כהנים *kohanim*. So even though it's not at a stage
yet where it could be eaten, nevertheless, it's not like you've taken
away something that would have gone on the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbayach*. So
again, we really have a problem here as to what do you
do with קרבנות korbonos, *korbanot*, when you are נהנה ne'eneh *neheneh* from
קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot*, if you can't just give the same קרבן korban
*korban* back. So we're here trying to approximate it as we're trying
to do some substitute is to give something that is just burnt
on the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbayach*, whether it's an עולה Olah. *olah* or
whether it's קטורת ktoret, *ketoret*. But it is important to note that
while this idea of burnt on the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbayach* parallels the
case of the אימורי קדשי קדשים kadshei kodoshim *imuray kodshay kodashim*, it
does not really parallel the בשר קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim *basar kodshay
kodashim*. Okay, and nevertheless, that's what you would do. Now of course
the same obvious הלכה *halacha* would apply to the אימורי קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim. *imuray kodshay kodashim*. Okay, obviously that certainly gets burnt on
the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbayach*. But the חידוש *chiddush* is even the בשר
קדשי קדשים *basar kodshay kodashim*, which never would have gone on the
מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbayach*, this is what you do, you have to bring
some type of a קרבן korban *korban*. So, of course, so you
give something you fully divest yourself of it, something that fully goes
to the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbayach* is either the עולה olah. *olah* or
the קטורת ketoret, *ketoret*.
Forgive me for just disagreeing, but the, you know, I'm going to
go back to my point of the עצים *eitzim*. I thought the
עצים *eitzim* is a קרבן korban? *korban* that even had a question
of whether you salt it or not.
Oh, that's true. No, no, no, you could, it depends which type
of עצים *eitzim* you're נודב *nodeiv*. You could be, if you're נודב
עצים *nodeiv eitzim* qua קרבן korban, *korban*, that's true. So that would
be a question according to לוי *Levi* that's interested in, according that's,
you know, something that is not as classic animal or מנחה mincha,
*mincha* קרבן korban. *korban*, what about that case? Although I would still
say that that's a little bit more of a bizarre situation than
קטורת ketoret *ketoret*. Alright, I don't know, maybe he would say yes.
Okay, so let's take a look. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
goes on, so now it says the following.
Okay, fine. תניא כוותיה דרב *Tanya kevasay d'Rav*, we taught like רב
Rav's *Rav*. הנהנה מדמי חטאת chatas, ומדמי אשם asham, *Haneheneh midmay chatat
umidmay asham*, so somebody benefited from the money of a חטאת chatas,
*chatat*, money of an אשם asham, *asham*. That's going to be easy,
you take money, if you stole money you just give back money.
So עד שלא קרב kariv. חטאתו *Ad shelo karav chatato*, before it
was offered up, actually what it really means before it was bought.
No, no, it was before it was bought. Or maybe it could
mean קרב *karav*, because it does you wait for there to be
a מום *mum* and then you transfer the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* with
a מום *mum*. But anyway, if you still have the option of
using this money, then what do you do? יוסיף ויביא חטאתו *Yosif
vayavi chatato*. So then you go ahead, you give back the money
plus the fifth, and you use that to bring now a bigger
חטאת chatas. *chatat*. ועד שלא קרב אשמו *V'ad shelo karav ashamo*, you
haven't yet קרב *karav*, but again, really means if you haven't yet
bought the אשם *asham*. Or maybe it could mean קרב *karav*, because
it does you wait for there to be a מום *mum* and
then you transfer the קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* with a מום *mum*. But
anyway, if you still have the option of using this money, then
what do you do? יוסיף ויביא אשמו *Yosif vayavi ashamo*. So then
you give it back plus the extra fifth, and now you bring,
use that money to bring an אשם *asham* or חטאת chatas, *chatat*
instead, if you still have that option. Fine, that's פשוט *pashut*. קרב
חטאתו *Karav chatato*, now let's say the חטאת chatas *chatat* was קרב
*karav*. So now you have money that you will describe exactly when
this occurs, after you became aware. But I'll just jump ahead and
tell you what occurs after you became aware. You became aware, "Oh
my God, I accidentally took from this money, it was put aside
for חטאת chatas *chatat* money," because we know also is a case
of שוגג *shogeg*. I think, "Oh my gosh, look what I did.
I accidentally did it." Right now what would we say your obligation
is, give back the money.
Now after you were supposed to give back money, somehow your, again
maybe it wasn't your חטאת chatas *chatat* money, that חטאת chatas *chatat*
goes ahead,
somebody now
used other money, well, other money and bought a חטאת chatas *chatat*
and was קרב *karav*.
No, meaning let's say I put three dollars in and I took
two dollars out and then
use those two, fine, or whatever the case is, some of that
money, anyway, the חטאת chatas *chatat* was now brought. After you became
aware that you were obligated. At the moment you became aware you
were obligated, what you should have done was given back the money.
Okay, so you had an obligation to give חטאת chatas *chatat* money
and now that חטאת chatas *chatat* was brought. So now if because
you're obligated to give חטאת chatas *chatat* money and now the חטאת
chatas *chatat* was brought, the money you should have given, although it's
not something concrete, is like a חטאת שנתכפרו בעליה באחר Chatat she-nitkapru
ba'aleha be-acher *chatat shenitkapru ba'aleha b'acher*. That's you, the, some other חטאת
chatas, *chatat* was brought instead of this money, right, something else was
brought instead of this money. So what's the normal הלכה *halacha* if
another חטאת chatas, *chatat* was brought instead of this קרבן korban *korban*?
Then it has to die. So now what do you do with
the money? It says, יוליך לים המלח Yolich l'yam hamelach. *Yolich l'yam
hamelach*. It says, קרב חטאתו *karav chatato*, if before you paid, you
gave the money back, and but after you became aware, the חטאת
chatas *chatat* was brought, then יוליך לים המלח yolich le-yam hamelach. *yolich
l'yam hamelach*. Take the money and throw it to the sea, it's
like a חטאת chatas שנתכפרו בעליה באחר *chatat shenitkapru ba'aleha b'acher*. כבר
קרב אשמו *Kvar
karav ashamo*, now let's say however it was not a case of
a חטאת chatas, *chatat* but a case of an אשם *asham*. So
what happens by an אשם *asham* if you have a second one
and the first one is brought? Then the one, the extra one
goes to becomes an עולה olah *olah*. Okay, so therefore if the
אשם *asham* was already brought, יפלו לנדבה yipelu le-nedavah, *Yiplu l'nedava*, the
money goes for an עולת ציבור olas tzibur. *olas tzibbur*. Okay, so
that's the case of what you took was money or you benefited
from money, some of the money, all the money, etc. If it's
still money and you can still buy something, you give it back
and you buy. If you became aware and then the thing was
brought, you have to treat it like a leftover קרבן korban, and
do the appropriate thing. Either throw it to ים המלח Yam Hamelach
or buy an עולה. olah Now, and the משנה mishna says like
this, so that's money. Now we haven't gotten—that's interesting, but it's not
as challenging as the case of when you are נהנה ne'eneh from
the קרבן korban, itself. Okay, so let's take a look. הנהנה מקדשי
קדשים לפני זריקת דמים ואימורי קדשי קדשים לאחר זריקת דמים. Hane'eneh mikadshei
kodoshim lifnei zrikas damim v'imurei kadshei kodoshim l'achar zrikas damim. Exactly רב
Rav. case, you benefited from קדשי קדשים before זריקת דמים zrikas damim
or אימורים imurim after זריקת דמים. zrikas damim. So this is cases
where there's still מעילה me'ilah and even as I said the בשר
of קדשי קדשים is not going on the מזבח. mizbe'ach, Nevertheless, מה
שנהנה יפלו לנדבה, ma she'ne'ene yiplu linidava, what you benefited you goes
for again נדבה nidava which means עולת ציבור. olas tzibur. So that
is again רב. Rav. Okay, now כל קרבנות המזבח למזבח. kol korbonos
hamizbeach l'mizbeach. This next becomes a little redundant. Anything so that if
you benefited from a
קרבן korban that would go on the altar, it goes back to
the altar, and that's why we do an עולת נדבה. olas nidava.
קרבנות בדק הבית לבדק הבית. Korbonos bedek habayis l'bedek habayis. Interesting phrase
קרבנות, korbanot but the point is if you are נהנה ne'eneh from
money from the Temple treasury, לבדק הבית, l'bedek habayis, then it goes
back to the Temple treasury. Now just spelling it out—and then it
spells it out yet again. קרבנות ציבור לנדבת ציבור. Korbonos tzibur linidvas
tzibur. If you benefited from a
קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, you give back to a נדבת ציבור, nidvas
tzibur, you give that back as an עולה. olah. So basically it's
a little redundant but overwhelmingly what it basically said is what do
you do if you were נהנה ne'eneh. from a קרבן? korban You
give it back as a נדבה nidava which means an עולת ציבור.
You give it back as an עולה olah, that gets burnt even
if you took from let's say even בשר קדשי קדשים that normally
would not be burnt but would be eaten.
And certainly the אימורים. imurim.
And certainly the אימורים. imurim. Okay, so that's exactly like רב. Now
there is a little bit of a problem, a conflict, because it
did say initially that if it was a חטאת, chatas. it goes
לים המלח. l'yam hamelach. And here it says, seems to be whatever
you benefit from, it goes as a—it goes as a נדבת ציבור.
nidvas tzibur. So we'll take a look, the גמרא Gemara, is going
to get to it. Okay, כגופא קשיא.
K'gufa kashya. What happened if it goes—if it was from the treasury
that you stole?
Then you give back to the treasury. The money, the objects. Sure.
Right.
But I mean—if I was נהנה ne'eneh from a cup of treasury
then I give money for a new cup? I don't have to
like—bring the cup back?
Correct, but you—but it's also you take what you benefited, not the
value of the thing. Because there's two types of מעילה me'ilah basically:
stealing מעילה me'ilah where what you give back is the value of
what you've taken, and הנאת מעילה. hana'as me'ilah. Okay, where what you
give back is what you were נהנה. ne'eneh Yeah, yours is a
good question which is: if the object is still around and it
was a stealing type of a thing, can I just take the
object and give it back and so on?
Right, it's a good question. All right, we'll see about it. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay.
הגופא קשיא, Hagufa kashya, there's an internal contradiction here.
עד שלא קרב חטאתו יביא בדמי חטאתו. Ad shelo karev chataso yavi
bidmei chataso. If you haven't yet bought the חטאת, chatas. then use
the money and the extra fifth and buy a חטאת. chatas? משקרב
חטאתו, Mishekarev chataso, once you've brought the חטאת, chatas, what do you
do with the money? יוליך לים המלח. It goes to the Dead
Sea. So here it says that if you were נהנה ne'eneh from
a חטאת chatas? and you can no longer buy the חטאת chatas
because the חטאת chatas was already brought, you throw the money into
the Dead Sea.
וכדתני, U'kedasni, כל קרבנות המזבח למזבח. kol korbonos hamizbeach l'mizbeach. That whenever
you're נהנה nehene from a קרבן, Korban, you turn the money into
an עולה olah. and you bring it as a קרבן. Korban, לא
שנא דאיכפר בעלים ולא שנא דלא איכפר. Lo shena d'ikaper ba'aleha v'lo
shena d'lo ikaper. It doesn't matter if the original קרבן Korban has
been brought or not. Right? You get the contradiction? The first case
about the money, it says what do you do if the חטאת
chatas already brought? Then it's like מתה בעליה meisa ba'aleha and you
throw the money in the Dead Sea. The second case says: whenever
you're נהנה nehene from a קרבן, Korban what do you do? You
bring—you take the money value that you benefit and you bring it
as an עולה. olah. So why originally did we say that it
was a חטאת chatas case and it was brought, I have to
throw the money out? And here we say that I always bring
it as an עולה, olah. presumably even if the original חטאת chatas.
was already brought. So the גמרא Gemara says, רישא רבי שמעון היא
דאמר כל חטאת שנתכפרו בעליה תמות. Reisha Rabbi Shimon hi d'amar kol
chatas she'niskaperu ba'aleha tamus. It's actually two different opinions. So the רישא,
reisha, what do you do with חטאת chatas that the owners were
atoned for? So the first thing that says you throw the money
out is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says that any חטאת chatas
that the—that the owners were atoned for and you have this thing
that has קדושת חטאת, kedushas chatas, it has to die. הסיפא, Hasayfa,
top of י"ד עמוד א', yud daled amud aleph, רבנן. Rabbanan. And
the סיפא sayfa is the Rabbis that say no, that if the
owners are atoned, unless it's a very narrow special case, a normal
חטאת chatas the owners are atoned, you can use the חטאת chatas
as an עולה. olah. So here too you use the money as
an
עולה.
olah. Which case?
You're likely asking me too many questions. Anyway, but it's also distracting.
So I mean תוספות Tosafos has a whole discussion, there's some special
cases. Anyway, פיין. fayn. So now—so now what's the basic answer we've
got? Basically the answer is, and this is interesting because you could
have thought of another answer which might be at the end of
the גמרא, Gemara that the basic answer is: if it's a חטאת,
chatas you're supposed to bring another חטאת, chatas and then if you
can't bring another חטאת Chatat because the original one was brought. then
what you do with this is what the normal הלכות halachos are
for a חטאת Chatat that נתכפר באחר, niskaper b'acher, either throw it
into the ים המלח Yam HaMelach or go ahead and bring an
עולה. olah It's not that there's a general rule of bringing an
עולה. olah It's you bring the thing that you stole or נהנה
nehene from and then if it can't be brought you deal with
it about what happens if that can't be brought. Now that of
course raises a question because let's say I was נהנה nehene from
the, I don't know, the אימורים emurim of a שלמים, shelumim, right?
Why don't I have to bring a, you know, a שלמים shelumim
instead? Right? Well, so why is, if you really give the money
back for the same קרבן, Korban okay, so maybe, maybe then they're
not because the אימורים emurim of קדשים קלים always go on מזבח,
mizbeach
so that you can never give back a שלמים shelumim because that's
not all going to go to the מזבח, mizbeach, you have to
give back an עולה. olah, Do you understand my question? Meaning we
have two models here about what you do when you give back
מעילה me'ilah money. One model is
if you took stuff that goes on a מזבח, mizbeach, give back
an עולה olah. because an עולה olah. goes on a מזבח mizbeach
or קטורת, but whatever, something that's going to be burnt. The other
model is give back the same type of thing you took. Okay,
now that seems to be what we're saying now. If you took
a חטאת, Chatat give back a חטאת. Chatat Oh, but you can't
bring another חטאת. Chatat Well what do you do if you can't
bring another חטאת? Chatat Some people say it has to die, some
say throw it in the ים המלח, Yam HaMelach, some people say
it's brought as עולה, olah? you bring it as an עולה. olah
That's not the model of if you took from the מזבח, mizbe'ach.
give back an עולה. olah, That's the model of give back what
you took. But if that's true, then why did we say before
categorical statements of give back an עולה? olah. So it's actually interesting
that everything will wind up an עולה olah. even based on the
model of give back what you took. Why? Let's see. Let's say
you took an עולה, olah. so give back what you took, an
עולה. olah, Let's say you took a חטאת, Chatat so what do
you give back? Well, if you're not going to say ים המלח,
Yam HaMelach, so what do you do with a leftover חטאת? Chatat,
עולה. olah Let's say you took a שלמים, shlamim, an אשם, what
do you do if you have a leftover אשם, extra money? עולה.
olah. Let's, so the עולה, olah. the only example is let's say
it's like a שלמים. shlamim. Okay, well there since the שלמים shlamim
you can't give back a שלמים shlamim because you only took from
the part that goes on the מזבח, mizbe'ach. and therefore if you
give back a שלמים shlamim three quarters of it is not going
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach. so by a שלמים shlamim there you have
to give an עולה olah because that substitutes for the אימורים. emurim.
But by the other things, it's a variation of giving back what
you took. So those really seem to be the two models. That's
what the גמרא Gemara said. First you say ים המלח, Yam HaMelach,
then you say an עולה. olah. It sounds like one is give
back what you took, the other is always do an עולה. olah.
And the answer is, the answer is really it's all assuming give
back what you took, except that there's a debate what do you
do with a חטאת Chatat, leftover money. So the רישא Reisha says
ים המלח, Yam HaMelach, that's what you do with an animal חטאת
Chatat, leftover, and the other says no, use it as an עולה
olah because that's an opinion that says you don't, you would even
if it was a leftover animal, that's what you would do.
Yeah, so you're saying so if I was נהנה nehene from the
meat inappropriately, right, then nothing because there's no מעילה me'ilah before...
yes, נהנה nehene from the שלמים, shlamim, correct.
Okay, so אמר רב גביהא מבי כתיל לרב אשי הכי אמר אביי,
amar Rav Gbiha m'Bei Katil l'Rav Ashi hachi amar Abaye, you know
so he says you know what אביי Abaye said the same thing,
רישא Reisha רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon וסיפא v'Seifa רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay, the
רישא Reisha is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon the סיפא Seifa is the
רבנן. Rabbanan. Now that again shifts us to this conceptual model of
give back what you took, not give back an עולה. olah But
I'm going to see, we'll see at the end, it might shift
back in a minute. So אמר רבא הכל מודים שאם נהנה מבשר
קדשי קדשים שנטמא ומאימורי קודם זריקה,
amar Rava hakol modim she'im nehene mibsar kodshei
kodashim she'nitma u'me'emurei kodem zrika, let's put it in, ומאימורי קדשים קלים
לאחר שהעלן דפטור. u'me'emurei kodshim kalim l'achar she'helan d'pattur. Now this is
and the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא. peshita. Now this statement is far
from פשיטא peshita but the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא. peshita. He says
like this, everybody agrees that if you were נהנה nehene from the
meat of קדשי קדשים שנטמא, kodshei kodashim she'nitma,
that you, that you're פטור. pattur. Now why are you פטור? pattur?
If, if so let's take, let's think about what the scenario is.
If you were נהנה nehene from them before זריקה, zrika, right, then
it has nothing to do with the fact that they became טמא,
tamei, then you're נהנה nehene from... I'm sorry, no no, excuse
me, what did I say? If you were נהנה nehene from them
after זריקה, zrika, so of course you're פטור, pattur, right? Because then
the זריקה zrika was מתיר mattir them. It has nothing to do
with the fact שנטמא. she'nitma. And נטמא nitma doesn't make you more
פטור, pattur, certainly it wouldn't make you more חייב chayav and so
on. If you were נהנה nehene... from it before זריקה, zrika, then
why are you פטור? pattur? Our very first משנה mishna of the
first פרק perek said that if a problem occurred before זריקה zrika
and the זריקה zrika was never מתיר mattir it, right, so then
it remains an איסור מעילה. issur me'ilah. So if the meat of
קדשי קדשים became טמא tamei before זריקה, zrika, then you should remain
חייב chayav even after זריקה. zrika. Yes, are you still with me?
He basically says you're פטור pattur by the meat of קדשי קדשים
שנטמא. kodshei kodashim she'nitma. But we're talking about, if the זריקה zrika
was good of course you're פטור. pattur. If זריקה zrika hadn't yet
occurred or the זריקה zrika occurred after it became טמא, tamei, then
our very first משנה mishnah said, right, that מעילה me'ilah still applies.
So this is definitely far from פשיטא. peshita. So I will tell
you רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos, have two very different reads about
this. So רש"י Rashi or Pseudo-רש"י Rashi says, let me just double
check all of
this...
Right. Okay. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says, let’s read it תוספות Tosafos,
*Tosafot*’s way and then I’ll go back and tell you רש"י Rashi
*Rashi*’s way. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says we’re talking that
that it became טמא tamei, *tamei* after זריקת הדם zrikas hadam. *zerikat
hadam*. Okay. It became טמא tamei. *tamei* after זריקת הדם zrikas hadam.
*zerikat hadam*. Now, of course it became טמא tamei *tamei* after זריקת
הדם zrikas hadam *zerikat hadam*, of course there’s no מעילה meila, *me'ilah*.
No, because what happens to קדשים שנפסלו *kodshim she'nifsalu*? It became טמא
tamei *tamei* after זריקת הדם zerikat ha-dam *zerikat hadam*, so this meat
now could have been eaten by the כהנים *kohanim* and it became
טמא tamei *tamei*. What would you normally do by קדשים שנפסלו *kodshim
she'nifsalu*? Burn it, right? There’s a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to burn it.
Okay. So the question is, oh, maybe now that it becomes טמא
tamei. *tamei* and there’s a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to burn it, it’s
not yet נעשה מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato*. Right? It’s not about eating it.
It’s about a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to burn it. And maybe therefore
there’s an idea it’s not yet נעשה מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato*. And maybe
therefore there would be an idea of מעילה meila *me'ilah*. Okay, now
of course it’d be pretty funny something went out of מעילה meila.
*me'ilah* and then came back in, but that’s what he’s talking about.
So let’s read it תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*’s way and then we’ll go
back to read it רש"י Rashi *Rashi*’s way. הכל מודים *Hakol modim*,
and here the הכל מודים *Hakol modim* is רב *Rav* and רב
יוחנן *Rav Yochanan*. So we’re circling back to רב *Rav* and רב
יוחנן *Rav Yochanan*. רב *Rav* and רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* had debated
whether it was נעשה מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato* before you took the ashes
out. They would still agree that the following: כי נטמא בשר קדשי
קדשים שנטמא basar kodshei kodashim shenitma. *ki nitmai basar kodshei kodshim she'nitma*,
if the meat became טמא tamei. *tamei*, and now we’re reading it
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*’s way, after זריקה *zerikah*, even though there’s still a
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to burn it, או אימורי קדשים קלים לאחר שהעלם
*o emurei kodshim kalim leachar she'he'elam*, or the אימורי קדשים קלים *emurei
kodshim kalim* after they’re on the fire. And now this really makes
sense, because you would have said if after they’re on the fire
is enough to get them out of מעילה meila *me'ilah*? When normally,
what have we said, when does stuff normally come out of מעילה
meila. *me'ilah* that’s being burned? At what stage? As soon as they’re
put on the fire? No. תרומת הדשן terumas hadeshen *trumat hadeshen* minimally.
But they say in these two, even though that that would be
different, everybody would agree that you’re פטור *patur*. Now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says פשיטא pishita *pshita*. Again, the פשיטא pishita, *pshita* is quite
a funny question. מה קא משמע לן *mai kamashma lan*? What are
you losing? At now, of course, you would at least by the
second case it’s not פשיטא pshita *pshita* because the second case is
the case where, what do you call it, where it’s not yet
turned into ashes. But let’s see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*’s answer
is. מהו דתימא *mahu de-teima*, I might have thought, בשר קדשי קדשים
שנטמא *basar kodshei kodshim she'nitma* אית ליה מצות שריפה *is lei mitzvat
srefah* לכהנים *lakohanim*, again, okay,
that the meat of קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodshim* there’s still a מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah* of שריפה *srefah*, even though it became מותר muttar. *mutar*
to the כהנים *kohanim* once it became טמא *tamei* there’s a מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah* of שריפה *srefah*, אימורי קדשים קלים איכא מצוה mitzvah להפוכי
בצינורא *emurei kodshim kalim ika mitzvah le'hapuchei betzinora* and the אימורי קדשים
קלים *emurei kodshim kalim* that are burning on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbe'ach*,
there’s still a מצוה *mitzvah* to turn them up and
to finish burning them and turn them into ashes, קא משמע לן
דלא *ka mashma lan de'lo*, so it’s telling you that that’s not
true, that that those cases even though there’s a debate of when
they’re נעשה מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato* by the stuff that you have not,
the ashes that you have not cleaned off, here everybody would agree
that it’s not a נעשה מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato* problem and there’s no
מעילה meila? *me'ilah*. Now the question is why not? So there are
two scenarios. The one scenario is the meat that became מותר *mutar*
to eat and then it got טמא *tamei* and there’s a מצוה
*mitzvah* to burn. So that’s easy to explain why it’s not an
issue of נעשה מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato*. First of all, you could question
to what degree do we consider, what do we define as the,
as the, mitzvah to be done? There’s a lot of things that
are part of the process of the מקדש *Mikdash* and so on
and we wouldn’t say like this is its מצוה *mitzvah* is to
be, is to be burned. But even beyond that, once the meat
became מותר לכהנים *mutar lakohanim*, it went out of being קדשי השם
*kodshei Hashem*. Right? Not everything that’s אסור assur *assur* is,
is מעילה meila *me'ilah*, right? The קדשים קלים *kodshim kalim* is אסור
assur *assur* and it’s not מעילה meila. *me'ilah* until the אימורים *emurim*
after זריקת הדם zerikat hadam, *zerikat hadam*. So that’s easy. Just because
it’s not נעשה מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato* when it once it went out
of קדשי השם *kodshei Hashem* it’s not a problem. But the קדשים
קלים *kodshim kalim* is a different issue, because the קדשים קלים *kodshim
kalim*, they’re not turned into ashes, right? So why by the קדשים
קלים *kodshim kalim* would we not say that the מצוה *mitzvah* still
applies? And here, it seems like what we’re saying is, and this
by the way is a very important conceptual question is, why by
קדשים קלים *kodshim kalim* in general do we say, Michael this is
your point, we say there’s no מעילה me'ila *me'ilah* before זריקת הדם
zerikat hadam *zerikat hadam*? Why is that? It’s קודש *kodesh*, before זריקת
הדם zerikat hadam, *zerikat hadam* you’re not allowed to eat the meat,
let there be מעילה meilah, *me'ilah* on the meat. It’s still קודש
*kodesh*, right? And obviously we see that just because the קדושה *kedushah*
prevents you from benefiting from it is not enough. There has to
be this concept of, you know, like of קדשי השם *kodshei Hashem*,
כולו להשם kulo la-Hashem, *kulo la-Hashem*, okay, which doesn’t apply and actually
it’s different in קדשים קלים *kodshim kalim* and קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodshim*.
If you think about it. Both of those cases before זריקת הדם,
zerikat hadam you're not allowed to eat from the meat. Both of
those cases eventually you will be able to eat from the meat.
But nevertheless, by קודשי קודשים, kodshei kodshim, there's מעילה, meilah by קודשים
קלים, kodshim kalim, not. Because קודשי קודשים kodshei kodshim conceptually that קרבן
Korban, is like כולו להשם, kulo la-Hashem and therefore even when you
eat from the meat, that's as it were משולחן גבוה. mishulchan gavoah.
This one conceptually is not כולו להשם kulo la-Hashem, until after זריקת
הדם. So that's just being aware that being אסור and stuff. But
what we do see is that קודשים קלים kodshim kalim have to
essentially fight to get their מעילה meilah? status, right? So only after
זריקת הדם. Although the meat really should be the same, nevertheless, you
start much more less קודשי השם kodshei Hashem and only אימורין imurin
matter afterwards. So you could have just said that that's his point,
that even therefore when it comes to the question of
נעשית מצוותו, na'asis mitzvaso, by of the things of קודשי קודשים kodshei
kodshim that's כולו להשם, there in order to say נעשית מצוותו na'asis
mitzvaso it would have to turn into ashes, the ashes have to
be taken out, etc. Here, where like, you know, you're lucky to
be on the מזבח mizbe'ach as it were, as soon as the
basic מצוה was done, as soon as it started burning, we'll just
say that it's נעשית מצוותו na'asis mitzvaso at an earlier stage. So
that's saying that the difference here, the function of how the level
of קדושה the thing whether it's קודשי השם, kodshei Hashem, whether it's
קודשי קודשים kodshei kodshim or not, at least for the purposes of
מעילה. You know, this thing because it was so hard to get
in the מעילה category, even at an early stage of נעשית מצוותו
na'asis mitzvaso falls out. That's one way of saying it. תוספות, Tosafot
and you'll like this Michael, says no, maybe the whole issue has
to do with the פסוקים. pesukim. The פסוקים pesukim only mention the
idea of taking out the ashes by an עולה. olah. So maybe
the idea, there you go. So תוספות Tosafot says it here. Maybe
the idea of that there's a מצוה of תרומת הדשן terumas hadeshen,
or a מצוה of הוצאת הדשן hotza'as hadeshen only applies to קודשי
קודשים. kodshei kodshim. Maybe fundamentally the מצוה does not apply to קודשים
קלים. kodshim kalim. Okay, so this thing that the גמרא Gemara said,
but we
say it does, mean למימרא, le-memra, right?
No, he says that according to the מסקנא maskana not. I mean
you would clean up because you clean off the מזבח, mizbe'ach. but
to the point that there's a מצוה to remove it, and it's
an issue of נעשית מצוותו, na'asis mitzvaso, you would not say it.
Okay, so according to תוספות, Tosafot תוספות reads this, although the גמרא
Gemara says פשיטא pshita as far as I understand, תוספות reads this
that
number one, the meat of קודשי קודשים kodshei kodshim after זריקת הדם
became טמא, there's still מעילה. There's no מעילה? Why? That's obvious, because
even though that maybe is פשיטא, because even though you still have
a מצוה to burn it, it fell out of being קודשי השם
kodshei Hashem and therefore that clearly is not קדוש kadosh enough at
this stage, even though now it's אסור because it became טמא. That
is relatively simple. But the next point is that even stuff that's
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, אימורי קודשים קלים imurei kodshim kalim is different
than קודשי קודשים. kodshei kodshim. אימורי קודשים קלים imurei kodshim kalim as
soon as you, it starts burning, even though the גמרא Gemara, says
obviously you're supposed to turn it over and it's supposed to finish
getting burned, as soon as it starts burning no longer. So now
we have a difference. By קודשי קודשים kodshei kodshim it's not נעשית
מצוותו na'asis mitzvaso till ashes, till תרומת הדשן, till הוצאת הדשן. hotza'as
hadeshen. This is נעשית מצוותו na'asis mitzvaso as soon as it starts
burning. Why? I think because קודשים קלים kodshim kalim so it falls
out of מעילה much quicker. Or because as תוספות says, there's fundamentally
not a מצוה of ashes by קודשי קודשים, kodshei kodshim, it's only
by קודשים קלים. kodshim kalim. Could I ask a question?
Yes. So what usually happens to like the horns and the and
the hooves of an animal? Does the כהן kohen get that?
Yeah, I suppose. I mean I suppose it's like the leather of
the עולה olah.
that it's not... if I cut off the horn of an animal
that's a קודשי קודשים kodshei kodshim since the כהן kohen is never
going to get it, the מזבח mizbe'ach, is never going to get
it.
After it was שחט shachted or before? Either way. There's actually גמרא
Gemara about that in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah about using the horns
of an עולת שלמים olas shelamim for a שופר. shofar.
If memory serves, I think that גמרא Gemara makes it clear that
there is מעילה.
But what's your point? The point is that well that's exactly the
issue. That's my, oh,
probably would be like the leather of the עולה olah. that it's
not הותר לכהנים hutar le-kohanim until after the קרבן korban is קרב.
Okay, let's take a look. Now the גמרא says like this. כמאן
דלא? Ke-man d'la? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now we get back to
that משנה Mishnah. about what you do with the money. Again, it's
pretty funny why we introduced the whole what you do with the
money issue. הא דאמרת Ha de-amart כבר קרבה חטאת, kevar karva chatas,
יוליך לים המלח. When do we say that if he became if
the חטאת Chatat was already brought and you had הנאה hana'ah from
money, you throw the money into the ocean? That's הני מילי דאישתמודע
ליה קמי כפרה. hani mili d'ishtemoda lei kammai kapara. That's if it
became known to you before atonement.
Meaning that you became aware before the חטאת Chatat was brought that
you were נהנה ne'ena from חטאת. Chatat So then even if you
didn't set aside the money, conceptually now there was חטאת Chatat, money
you had to give. And then there was חטאת Chatat money you
had to give, and a חטאת Chatat was brought, so the חטאת
Chatat. money became נתכפרו בעליה באחר niskapru ba'aleha be-acher and the money
has to be thrown out the same way a חטאת Chatat would
have to die. אבל לאחר כפרה, Aval le-achar kapara, if after the
חטאת Chatat, was brought you found out, then יפלו לנדבה, then it
goes for a for an עולה. olah. Why? Because מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? אין מפרישין לכתחילה לאיבוד. Ein mafrishin le-chatchilah le-ibud. You don't set
aside money to get thrown out. So there, if you already were
obligated to set aside money and then its status changed and now
it became מיתת חטאת? misas chatas? No, חטאת למיתה chatas le-misah then
you throw it out. But if from the moment you were נהנה...
ne'ena you became aware, which is when your חיוב chiyuv kicks in,
okay, חטאת Chatat was already brought, in that type of a case,
when you became aware, there it was clear that there was no
חטאת Chatat that was going to be able to be brought. So
therefore the money does not, is not set aside to be thrown
out. Now it's not an issue about wastefulness. I think the real
point is it can't be a חטאת שנתכפרו בעליה באחר unless
you, that sort of חטאת virtually existed before the original one was
brought. Because then it's like you have this קדושת חטאת kedushat Chatat
and the other one was brought and therefore it's נתכפרו באחר. nitkapru
ba-acher. Okay, but if you became aware only after it was brought,
so then the whole חטאת only begins to exist once it was
already brought. So obviously you're not going to create a קדושת חטאת
kedushat Chatat when the, when fundamentally there's no longer even the concept
of a חטאת for this guy; it was already brought. So in
that type of a case, everybody would agree that you use the
money for an עולה. olah? Now I would suggest that that idea
is sort of similar
to the, once you introduce that idea it could also explain the
contradiction at the beginning and the end. Right, the contradiction that here
it says to throw the money out and at the end it
said you bring an עולה. olah And I could have said, when
do you, when is it the idea to throw the money out?
When you stole money and it's possible to give back money, then
we could talk about the idea that then you have to give
back the same type of thing you stole. Like because you stole
money you give back money and then it could be give back
a חטאת and then it becomes, oh, the other חטאת was brought,
throw the money in the ים המלח. Yam HaMelach. But if fundamentally
you stole a קרבן, korban not stole, you נהנה ne'ena from a
קרבן, so it never started with the idea of give back a
חטאת, right? If you נהנה ne'ena, from a חטאת, you don't give
back a חטאת, the חטאת is right here. So in that case,
everybody agrees that what you do if you נהנה from a קרבן
is you give an עולה. olah. So that's I think רבא's Rava's
distinction of when you became aware, do you become obligated in a
חטאת or obligated in an עולה? olah You won't become obligated in
an עולה olah, if the חטאת already exists. I would also say
you wouldn't become obligated in a חטאת, the flip, you wouldn't become
obligated in a חטאת if the חטאת was already brought. I would
say the same thing is the difference between the money and the
not money. If you stole money you could say give back what
you took. And therefore you could have a concept of give back
a חטאת. But if the חטאת is around and you נהנה, right,
there's no concept of give back a חטאת, the חטאת is there
and it exists. So in that case, everybody says you would give
an עולה. olah So with the end we are left with these
two models about what do you do, how do you give back
by a קרבן when it's not money? One model is give back
an עולה olah or something like it, קטורת, basically something that's כולו
למזבח. kulo la-mizbe'ach. And the other model the גמרא sort of had
here, but I would suggest in the end it's sort of being
pushed aside is, no, in theory give back the same type of
קרבן you took from, at least if it's קדשי קדשים. And that
opens the possibility of throwing money into ים המלח. Yam HaMelach. But
I would argue that that's only in the case of money and
that in the end really when it is a קרבן, it's always
giving back an עולה, giving back something that's כולו למזבח. kulo la-mizbe'ach.
So when it says here המפריש מעות לעולה, ha-mafrish ma'ot le-olah, it
was sort of besides the point, right?
Because, no, המפריש מעות לעולה ha-mafrish ma'ot le-olah is
the besides point, המפריש מעות לאיבוד ha-mafrish ma'ot le-ibud
when there's no חטאת to be brought. That's how I argue. Okay,
let's go on in the גמרא, in the משנה. Let's see if
we can finish the פרק. perek. הקומץ והלבונה, Ha-kometz ve-ha-levonah, this is
a big okay, so this is similar to thing about when status
is changed.
הקומץ והלבונה והקטורת ומנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח. Ha-kometz ve-ha-levonah ve-ha-ketoret u-minchat
kohanim u-minchat kohen mashiach. So all of these are things that are
completely burnt on the מזבח. Okay, the קומץ kometz and the לבונה,
levonah, the hand-breadth and the frankincense from the מנחה, the קטורת that
would be brought every day,
the מנחת כהנים minchat kohanim is fully burnt on the מזבח. ומנחת
נסכים, u-minchat nesachim, the flour and water that would come with
קרבנות. korbanot, מעילן משיקדשו, me'ilan mi-she-yukdashu, מעילה begins from the moment of
קדושה. That we know. קידשן בכלי הוכשר בכלי הוכשר ליפסל בטבול יום
ובמחוסר כפורים ובלינה. Kiddeshan bi-kli huchshar bi-keli huchshar le-hapasel be-tevul yom u-vi-mechusar
kippurim u-ve-linah. Once they get קדושת הגוף, kedushat ha-guf, right, then they
are הוכשר בכלי, huchshar bi-kli, then it's when, then they can have
all this high, this even residual טומאה tumah can affect them and
the idea of לינה linah begins. So that comes with, until now
we've been sort of saying that like בקורבנות be-korbanot certain things is
when the crust is, falls over, like קרבנות it's when it's שחט,
shachat, but there's a higher stage of קדושת הגוף kedushat ha-guf here
that now allows them to become טמא and לינה linah begins. וחייבין
עליהן משום נותר ומשום טמא. Ve-chayavin aleihen mishum notar u-mishum tamei. Now
normally then there's a third stage which is when נותר, notar, פיגול
pigul and טמא kick in. What's the third stage? When the blood
is sprinkled, when the קומץ kometz is put on the מזבח. But
there is no third stage here because here the whole thing gets
put on the מזבח. So because there's no third stage, all of
the status changes begin when it's put in the vessel. וחייבין עליו
משום נותר ומשום טמא, Ve-chayavin alav mishum notar u-mishum tamei, if you
leave it over to be נותר, notar, if you're טמא you eat
it you're חייב. chayav. There is no third stage ופיגול אין בה,
u-pigul ein bah, but there is no פיגול. pigul. Why not? We're
going to say this כלל, klal, this is the rule. כל שיש
לו מתירים, Kol she-yesh lo matirin, anything that has a מתיר, matir,
something that's done on the מזבח that makes the rest of it
okay. Even by an עולה that it's all going to be burnt,
the זריקת הדם makes it a good קרבן and then allows the
עולה to be put on the מזבח. So that type of... case,
all those things that have that thing that makes you makes you
יוצא yotzei, *yotze* before the rest and then you do whatever you
do with the rest of the קרבן *korban*, אין חייבין משום פיגול
לא זה ולא זה עד שיקרב המתיר *ein chayavin mishum pigul lo
zeh velo zeh ad sheyekrev hamatir*. So this is the general principle
that applies to all the משניות mishnayot, *mishnayot*. If there is one
final stage you do to make it a good קרבן *korban* before
then you do whatever you know you eat, you put it on
the מזבח *mizbeach*, whatever else you do, like זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam*
would be the example, classic case, then the פיגול *pigul* נותר *notar*
וטמא *vetamay* does not kick in until it becomes a good קרבן
*korban*, until the מתיר mattir *matir* has been done. Okay, and it's
also you get פיגול *pigul*. וכל שאין לו מתירין *vekol she-ein lo
matirin*, and anything that does not have מתיר *matir* that after you
put it in the כלי kli. *kli* or straight on the מזבח
*mizbeach*, that case כיון שקדש בכלי *kivan shekidesh bikli*, as soon as
it has קדושת הכלי *kedushat hakli* there is no final stage, חייב
chayav עליהן משום נותר וטמא *chayav aleihen mishum notar vetamay*. You get
נותר *notar* and טמא *tamay* ופיגול אין בו *upigul ein bo*. Why
don't you have פיגול *pigul*? Because again, פיגול *pigul* is when we
learn פיגול *pigul*, we learn the פסוקים *pesukim* or whatever, but it's
basically an idea of לא ירצה *lo yeratze*, the question of ירצה
לפיגולו *yeratze l'pigulo*, and there has to be an act of ריצוי
*ritzuy*, there has to be an act that makes it a קרבן
*korban* and then פיגול *pigul* then applies to what's left over. You
remember that idea by פיגול *pigul*. פיגול *pigul* you have to go
through the whole process and make it as if it were a
good קרבן *korban*, and then when you do, then the פיגול *pigul*
status applies to what's left. So if there is no left over,
if there only it's all on the מזבח *mizbeach*, not an עולה
*olah*. An עולה *olah* at least is left over because it becomes
an עולה *olah* זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam*. Okay, but this is there's
never something that's done on the מזבח *mizbeach* until it's all put
on, there is no פיגול *pigul*. Let's take a look at the
גמרא *Gemara*. The גמרא *Gemara* really just learns learns this from פסוקים
*pesukim* and with that we will finish the פרק *perek*. מנא הני
מילי *menani milei*? Where do I get this idea of these two
this is really the heart of the משניות *mishnayot* about when the
various stages apply? דתנו רבנן *detanu rabbanan*, we taught: יכול אין חייבין
משום טומאה tumah אלא בדבר שיש לו מתירין *yachol ein chayavin mishum
tumah ela bedavar sheyesh lo matirin*. Maybe there's no obligation for טומאה
tumah *tumah* only in things that the because the
you know maybe because only in things that are like a normal
קרבן *korban* that have זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam* that have מתירין *matirin*.
ודין הוא *vadin hu*, and makes a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. ומה
פיגול שהוא בידיעה אחת *umah pigul shehu bi-yediyah achat*, פיגול *pigul* only
applies with something that has מתירין *matirin*, right? As we just said,
only something is done to the מזבח *mizbeach* and the rest then
becomes okay becomes valid and you're יוצא yotzei *yotze*. So ומה פיגול
שהוא בידיעה אחת *umah pigul shehu bi-yediyah achat*, פיגול *pigul* is very
very weighty. Number one is you're חייב *chayav* in פיגול *pigul* even
when you just become aware of it once, right? Like a normal
חטא *cheit*. Anything any sin you do you don't need to be
aware ahead of time, you just need to be aware after. וקרבנו
קבוע *vekorbano kavua*, and you bring a standard קרבן *korban* if you
ate פיגול *pigul*. ולא הותר מכללו *velo hutar miklalo*, and there's never
any cases פיגול *pigul*'s allowed. So never although פיגול *pigul* is so
weighty, אין חייב אלא על דבר שיש לו מתירין *ein chayav ela
al davar sheyesh lo matirin*. There's no פיגול *pigul* status and you're
therefore you're not חייב *chayav* unless it was a type of a
thing like a קרבן *korban* which has a מתיר *matir*, which you
do something and then the rest becomes valid. Okay, טומאה
*tumah*, so טומאה *tumah* which is much more tenuous in terms of
its איסור *issur*, שבשתי ידיעות *she-bishtei yedi'ot*, you're only חייב *chayav* a
קרבן *korban* טומאה *tumah* if you were aware before you did the
sin that you were טמא *tamay* and after, to two knowledges. וקרבנו
עולה ויורד *vekorbano oleh ve-yored*, and you don't bring a fixed קרבן
*korban*, it changes its values depending on what you can afford so
you can actually bring a cheaper קרבן *korban*. והותרה מכללה *vehutzrah miklalah*,
and sometimes we override טומאה *tumah* if it's a ציבור *tzibbur* case.
So טומאה *tumah* is much more is much weaker. Nevertheless, אינו דין
שלא יהא חייב אלא על דבר שיש לו מתירין *eino din shelo
yehei chayav ela al davar sheyesh lo matirin*? So maybe also it
should you should only be חייב *chayav* even only like things like
a קרבן *korban* that has זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam* and that has
a מתיר *matir* not by things that all go on the מזבח
*mizbeach* and don't have a מתיר *matir*? So תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*,
it teaches: אמור אליהם לדרתיכם כל איש אשר יקרב asher yikrav מכל
זרעכם *emor aleihem ledoroteichem kol ish asher yikrav mikol zarechem* etc. So
this is a פסוק *pasuk* אל הקדשים לא יקרב *al hakodashim lo
yikrav* that tell them you know nobody should get close to the
קדשים *kodashim* when they are טמא *tamay*. Okay, so בכל הקדשים הכתוב
מדבר *bekhol hakodashim hakatuv medaber*, by all קרבנות *korbanot*, again exactly where
which part of the פסוק *pasuk* it's being מדייק *medayek* from but
maybe it certainly is כל אשר יקרב asher yikrav, *kol asher yikrav*
is every person but anyway understands the end of the
it understands that it's talking about all of the קרבנות *korbanot*. So
therefore anything that's כרת *kares* even if it doesn't have a מתיר
*matir*, even something like לבונה *levonah* or מנחת כהן *minchat kohen* etc.
Okay, so now and now the גמרא *Gemara* just ends. יכול יהא
חייבין עליהן מיד *yachol yehei chayavin aleihen miyad*? Maybe you're חייב *chayav*
טומאה *tumah* immediately even before the מתיר *matir* for something that does
have a מתיר *matir*? Maybe if I ate the meat before the
זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam*? Okay maybe there's מעילה *me'ilah* whatever
but nevertheless am I חייב *chayav* if I'm טמא *tamay*? Maybe right?
Maybe I'm טמא *tamay* before the מתיר *matir* is done as long
as I'm eating meat and I'm טמא *tamay*? So תלמוד לומר אשר
יקרב asher yikrav, *talmud lomar asher yikrav*. So what does that mean?
So let's take what where do you אשר יקרב asher yikrav. *asher
yikrav* you see the idea that it's only when it's only after
the מתיר *matir*? So אמר רבי אליעזר *amar rabbi eliezer*, וכי יש
נוגע שהוא חייב *vechi yesh noge'a shehu chayav*? Because the simple sense
of the פסוק *pasuk* is anybody who comes close אשר יקרב *asher
yikrav*, comes close and is טמא *tamay*, you get כרת *kares*. Now
that's not true. You're not חייב כרת *chayav kares* if you're טמא
*tamay* and you touch it. You're only חייב כרת *chayav kares* if
you eat it. So why does the תורה *Torah* refer to eating
it בטומאה betumah. *betumah* as יקרב *yikrav*? To tell you. To do
the following: הכיצד? כל דבר שיש לו מתירים Kol davar sheyesh lo
mattirin אינו חייב עד שיקרבו מתירים. eino chayav ad sheyikrevu mattirin. That
anything it means אשר יקרב means after it has been offered, or
it's actually expressed, or רש"י says after it's maybe, so anything that
is אשר יקרב, anything that the part that needs to be offered
was offered, then you're חייב if you eat it בטומאה. וכל דבר
שאין לו מתירים, Vechol davar she'ein lo mattirin, but if there is
no מתירים, mattirin, there's no אשר יקרב, then אינו חייב עד שיקדש
בכלי. eino chayav ad sheyikadesh bekli. You do not need to be
put it on the מזבח, obviously then you wouldn't even have a
scenario, since we know it applies to all קרבנות, that would apply
therefore after it's put into the כלי. kli הדרן לך חטאת העוף.
Hadran lach Chatas Ha'of. So basically the principle is, and this is
the principle of all the משניות, when you sanctify it, there's מעילה,
when it reaches the first stage of קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf is
the idea of טומאה of טומאה and לינה, linah, so like קרבן
it's שחיטה, shechitah, by other types of things it's a כלי or
the קרום krum forms and so on. And if there's מתירים, mattirin,
פיגול, נותר, וטמא pigul, notar, vetamei is when it's what we just
said, when the מתיר is done, somehow learned from אשר יקרב. And
when it is something that doesn't have מתירים, mattirin, then everything of
all those statuses apply when it's הוקדש בכלי. hukdash bekli. I guess
I'll just say one final thing about the סוגיא sugya before because
it's interesting about the fact of the broad statement about בשר קדשי
קדשים שנטמא. רש"י'ס Rashi's גרסא girsa had קודם זריקה. kodem zerikah. רש"י
actually says that essentially it sounds like a variation of רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, that since the זריקת הדם,
since the meat there's no benefit to it now, it's not going
on the מזבח, nobody can eat it, in that type of a
case there's no מעילה for if on the meat if זריקת הדם
even if the meat is פסול pasul is טמא. Now תוספות strongly
argues on that because תוספות says that was a debate and רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva only said it by יוצא, he didn't say it
by other פסולים. psulim. The גמרא never would have said פשיטא according
to that by רבא. Rava. It is worth noting in the simple
reading of רבא'ס Rava's statement that even if the meat can't be
eaten at all, once there's זריקת הדם, it's a variation of רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Remember רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva יוצא that after זריקת
הדם no מעילה? So it's possible to read רבא Rava the same
way and he would apply it even to טמא. But it's very
unusual that the גמרא would say פשיטא and it really thinks that's
better, much better פשט pshat is תוספות that it's talking about after
it became מותר. הדרן עלך. Hadran alach.